[Fate Chooses You]
[운명이 당신을 선택합니다]
[Episode 2]
[2회]
Lu Huai.
루 화이.
You'll be executed the day after tomorrow.
당신은 내일 모레 처형될 것입니다.
Although your case
비록 당신의 경우
was tried by the Court of Judicial Review itself
에 의해 시도되었다 사법심사재판소 그 자체
and the verdict is already set in stone,
그리고 판결은 이미 확정되었습니다.
according to procedure,
절차에 따라
I still have to ask:
아직 물어볼 게 있어요:
Lord Lu,
루 경,
do you have any grievances to declare
do you have any grievances to declare
or any case to appeal?
신고할 불만 사항이 있나요
No.
아니면 항소할 사건이 있나요?
I was thinking
아니요.
I might as well marry a death row prisoner
난 생각하고 있었어
to dispel the negative energy around me.
사형수와 결혼하는 게 나을 것 같아
I'd also offer some money
내 주변의 부정적인 에너지를 없애기 위해.
to compensate his family.
돈도 좀 주겠어요
But unfortunately,
가족들에게 보상을 하기 위해.
he has no family,
하지만 안타깝게도
not even relatives or friends.
그 사람은 가족이 없어
Actually, this Lord Lu
친척이나 친구도 아닙니다.
used to be quite decent.
사실 이 루 경
Though somewhat lazy,
꽤 괜찮은 편이었는데.
he was fair as an official.
다소 게으른 편이지만
He's been working here in Wei County for 5 or 6 years
그는 공무원으로서 공정했습니다.
and never oppressed any civilians.
그는 여기 웨이현에서 일하고 있어요 5~6년 동안
I don't know why
그리고 결코 민간인을 억압하지 않았습니다.
he suddenly lost his way
왜인지 모르겠어
and committed such a terrible crime.
갑자기 길을 잃었어
I visited his residence.
그리고 이런 끔찍한 범죄를 저질렀습니다.
It was very empty
나는 그의 집을 방문했다.
and quite simple.
아주 비어 있었어
I just don't understand,
아주 간단합니다.
with no family,
이해가 안 돼요
what's the point of embezzling so much money?
가족도 없이
What use could it be to him?
요점이 뭐야? 그렇게 많은 돈을 횡령했다고?
Who knows?
그에게 무슨 소용이 있겠습니까?
That's why I have a feeling that
누가 알겠어요?
he doesn't seem like that kind of person.
그래서 나는
Don't overthink it.
그 사람은 그런 사람 아닌 것 같은데.
You've already joined the immortal sect.
지나치게 생각하지 마십시오.
You shouldn't be involved in these
당신은 이미 불멸의 종파에 가입했습니다.
worldly matters.
당신은 이런 일에 관여하면 안 돼요
You only had a few days of connection with him.
세상적인 문제.
There's no need to know too much,
접속한 지 며칠밖에 안 됐어요 그와 함께.
lest it brings you unnecessary trouble.
너무 많이 알 필요는 없어요
[Wei County Government]
그것이 당신을 데려오지 않도록 불필요한 문제.
This case
[웨이 현 정부]
didn't need such a severe sentence.
이 사건
It was only because
그렇게 엄중한 선고는 필요 없었어요.
he insisted on getting Lord Liang involved
그 이유는
that it ended up like this.
그는 Liang 경을 개입시키겠다고 고집했어요
If he'd be willing to submit a formal petition
결국 이렇게 됐다고.
and admit his mistakes,
만약 그가 기꺼이 제출할 의향이 있다면 공식적인 청원서
then even if he'd be sentenced to
그리고 자신의 실수를 인정하고,
beheading,
그렇다면 그가 형을 선고받더라도
it would still be far better than death by 1,000 cuts.
참수,
My Lord.
그래도 그보다는 훨씬 나을 거야 1,000컷으로 사망.
You are kind-hearted, My Lord.
나의 주님.
It's Lu Huai who's being unreasonable.
당신은 마음이 친절하십니다, 나의 주님.
Even if he's lucky enough to escape this time,
불합리한 것은 Lu Huai입니다.
he won't escape the next.
운 좋게 탈출하더라도 이번에는
Lu Huai
그는 다음에서 탈출하지 않을 것입니다.
is an orphan.
루 화이
His parents died early,
고아입니다.
and he has no other relatives.
그의 부모님은 일찍 돌아가셨어
He came from the frontier army.
그에게는 다른 친척이 없습니다.
After earning several military merits
그는 국경군에서 왔습니다.
at the frontier,
여러 가지 군사 공로를 쌓은 후
he was recommended by someone
국경에서
and then appointed to Wei County.
그는 누군가에게 추천을 받았어요
Why is it stated here that
그런 다음 웨이 카운티에 임명되었습니다.
he still has family?
여기에
This was newly recorded a couple of days ago.
그 사람 아직 가족이 있어요?
He recently got married,
새로 녹음한 거예요 며칠 전.
to a woman who's also from Wei County.
그는 최근에 결혼했어요
Her surname's Xin.
역시 웨이현 출신의 여성에게.
[Madam Lu, née Xin. The rest's unknown.]
그녀의 성은 신(Xin)이다.
Here's your dish, Sir.
[루 부인, 성은 신. 나머지는 알 수 없습니다.]
Please enjoy.
여기 요리가 있습니다, 선생님.
Have you heard?
즐겨주세요.
Lu Huai is going to be executed.
들어보셨나요?
If you ask me, Lu Huai
Lu Huai는 처형될 예정입니다.
brought it upon himself.
저에게 묻는다면 Lu Huai
He leveraged those few military merits
그것을 스스로 가져 왔습니다.
to snag an official position,
그는 그 몇 가지 군사적 장점을 활용했습니다
yet he showed no gratitude.
공식적인 자리를 차지하기 위해
Instead, he colluded with corrupt merchants
그러나 그는 감사의 표시를 하지 않았습니다.
and drove up grain prices,
대신 그는 다음과 공모했다. 부패한 상인
causing the deaths of countless people!
곡물 가격을 올렸어요
Money corrupts the heart.
수많은 사람들의 죽음을 초래한!
For him to do such things,
돈은 마음을 부패시킵니다.
who knows
그 사람이 그런 일을 하려면
how much he profited from it?
누가 알겠어
Thankfully, Lord Liang was wise
그는 그것으로 얼마나 이익을 얻었나요?
and sentenced him to death by 1,000 cuts.
고맙게도 Liang 선생님 현명했어
It's truly
그리고 그에게 형을 선고했다 1,000컷으로 사망.
satisfying to see justice served.
정말이야
It's truly satisfying!
정의가 구현되는 것을 보는 것이 만족스럽습니다.
Yes, indeed.
정말 만족스럽습니다!
Attendant, the bill please!
네, 그렇습니다.
You gentlemen are supposedly well-educated scholars,
승무원님, 계산서 주세요!
yet you don't investigate the truth behind matters.
여러분 아마도 교육을 잘 받은 학자들,
[Tang You]
그런데 넌 조사를 안 해? 문제 뒤에 숨은 진실.
You only repeat what others say,
[탕 유]
barking at shadows like dogs,
당신은 다른 사람들이 말하는 것만 반복합니다.
and you still have the nerve to sit here
개처럼 그림자를 보고 짖어대
talking so shamelessly.
아직도 여기 앉을 용기가 있으신가요
It's truly laughable.
너무 뻔뻔하게 얘기함.
Who are you talking about?
정말 웃기다.
You guys, of course.
누구에 대해 이야기하고 있습니까?
A bunch of fools ignorant of the law,
물론이죠.
unable to tell right from wrong,
바보들의 무리 법에 무지해서
and incapable of discerning the wise from the foolish.
옳고 그름을 구분할 수 없어
Who are you?
그리고 분별력이 없다 어리석은 자 중에서 현명한 자.
We're just having a casual conversation here.
누구세요?
What does it have to do with you?
우리는 단지 여기서 가벼운 대화를 나누는 중이에요.
What you're saying is wrong,
그게 당신과 무슨 관련이 있나요?
and I can't stand hearing it.
당신이 말하는 것은 틀렸습니다.
Can't stand it?
나는 그 말을 듣는 것을 참을 수 없습니다.
Could it be
참을 수 없나요?
you're a supporter of that corrupt official,
그럴 수도 있지
and since your boss is about to die,
그리고 당신의 상사가 곧 죽을 것이기 때문에
you said that out of fear?
무서워서 그런 말을 했나?
Corrupt official?
오리?
Just look at you guys—
너희들을 좀 봐—
ignorant, petty, jealous
무지하고, 하찮고, 질투심이 많다
good-for-nothings—
쓸모없는 것—
the fact that even people like you managed to
당신 같은 사람도 있다는 사실 그럭저럭
survive that flood
그 홍수에서 살아남아
shows that
shows that
he still wasn't greedy enough.
그는 아직 욕심이 부족했습니다.
You...
당신은...
Ignore him.
그를 무시하세요.
Miss!
놓치다!
Let's have a drink together.
같이 한잔하자.
Please settle the bill.
요금을 정산해주세요.
Alright, alright.
알았어, 알았어.
Please come again.
다시 오세요.
Come take a look! Check out what we've got!
와서 보세요! 우리가 무엇을 가지고 있는지 확인해보세요!
Who are you people?
여러분은 누구입니까?
Who are you looking for?
당신은 누구를 찾고 있나요?
Are you Mrs. Lu,
루 부인이신가요?
Lord Lu Huai's wife?
Lu Huai 경의 아내?
Yes, I am.
네, 그렇습니다.
Officers, may I ask
장교님들, 물어봐도 될까요
what brings you here?
무슨 일로 여기까지 왔어?
The day after tomorrow
내일 모레
is his execution day.
그의 처형일이다.
According to the rules,
규칙에 따르면,
family members can visit the prison one last time
가족이 감옥을 방문할 수 있습니다. 마지막으로
to say their final goodbyes.
마지막 작별 인사를 하기 위해.
It must be no later than 7 PM tomorrow.
늦어도 내일 오후 7시까지는 되어야 합니다.
Don't miss the time.
시간을 놓치지 마세요.
Final goodbyes...
마지막 작별 인사...
Didn't you say you were leaving?
떠난다고 하지 않았나요?
Yes, I am leaving.
네, 나갑니다.
I haven't finished the tasks my master assigned me,
나는 할 일을 끝내지 않았어 내 주인이 나에게 할당했어요,
and I can't delay any longer.
더 이상 지체할 수 없습니다.
I've found the flower.
꽃을 찾았어요.
When I was there,
내가 거기 있었을 때,
I ran into 2 young beggars.
나는 두 명의 젊은 거지를 만났습니다.
They probably saw the house was empty
아마 집이 비어 있는 걸 봤을 거예요
and moved in.
이사를 왔어요.
Want me to go and chase them out?
내가 가서 그들을 쫓아내길 바라나요?
Don't bother.
귀찮게 하지 마세요.
The house's rented anyway.
어쨌든 집은 임대됐어요.
When the time comes,
때가 되면
the landlord will take it back.
집주인이 그것을 다시 가져갈 것입니다.
What kind of flower is this?
이것은 무슨 꽃인가요?
Hidden-heart Orchid.
숨겨진 심장 난초.
Hidden-heart Orchid?
숨겨진 하트 난초?
Never heard of it.
들어본 적도 없습니다.
By the way,
그런데,
I heard you're from the western border,
당신은 서쪽 국경에서 왔다고 들었어요,
so I asked around about
그래서 주변에
some customs from your region.
해당 지역의 일부 관습.
They say that a person must be buried in new clothes
사람이라고 하던데 새 옷을 입어야 해
to have a smooth journey to the afterlife,
사후 세계로의 원활한 여행을 위해
avoid being reborn as animals,
동물로 다시 태어나지 마세요
and be able to live with dignity in the next life.
그리고 당당하게 살아갈 수 있다 다음 생에는.
I didn't know
난 몰랐어
what colors and styles you like,
어떤 색상과 스타일을 좋아하는지
so I made a set
그래서 세트를 만들었어
according to my own taste.
내 취향대로.
Thanks a lot.
정말 감사합니다.
Do you want to try it on?
입어보고 싶나요?
No need.
필요하지 않습니다.
In the end, I'll just be nothing but a pile of bones anyway.
결국 난 아무것도 아닌 존재가 될 뿐이야 어쨌든 뼈 더미.
As long as something wraps around me, that's enough.
뭔가가 나를 감싸는 한, 그것으로 충분합니다.
Time to eat.
먹을 시간입니다.
This is the farewell meal.
이것이 송별식이다.
Eat well for your final journey.
마지막 여행을 위해 잘 드세요.
Just routine.
그냥 일상적이에요.
Why aren't you eating?
왜 안 먹어요?
I don't feel like eating.
먹고 싶지 않아요.
Lord Lu,
루 경,
is there truly no injustice
정말 불의는 없나요
in your case?
당신의 경우에는?
Public opinion has spoken.
여론이 이야기되었습니다.
How could there be any injustice?
어떻게 불의가 있을 수 있겠습니까?
I just can't help feeling
기분이 참 좋지 않네요
you're not a bad person.
당신은 나쁜 사람이 아닙니다.
The Court of Judicial Review itself determined my crimes
사법 심사 법원 스스로 내 범죄를 결정했어
and sentenced me to death by 1,000 cuts.
그리고 나한테 형을 선고했어 1,000컷으로 사망.
Over 100 memorials from censors
검열관이 만든 100개 이상의 기념물
have been submitted
제출되었습니다
to impeach me,
나를 탄핵하려고
and the common people out there
그리고 저 밖의 일반 사람들
all curse me
모두 나를 저주해
as a greedy and treacherous man.
탐욕스럽고 배신적인 사람으로.
You've heard it all,
다 들어보셨죠,
so why do you still think
그런데 왜 아직도 그렇게 생각해?
I'm not a bad person?
나 나쁜 사람 아니지?
Public clamor can confound right and wrong.
대중의 소란은 혼란스러울 수 있다 옳고 그름.
Give a dog a bad name and hang him.
개에게 나쁜 이름을 부여하고 매달아보세요.
Though we haven't interacted much,
비록 우리가 많이 교류하지는 않았지만,
I feel that you're not the same as
나는 당신이
what's being said about you out there.
와 같지 않다고 생각해요 밖에서 당신에 대해 무슨 말을 하는지.
If you were truly
당신이 정말로
greedy and cowardly,
탐욕스럽고 비겁해요
you'd have come asking me for help, right?
나한테 도움을 청하러 왔을 텐데요, 그렇죠?
After all, in the eyes of the world,
결국 세상의 눈에는
I'm also a cultivator.
나도 수련하는 사람이다.
Don't you...
그렇지 않나요...
Want to live?
살고 싶나요?
You can know someone's face but not their heart.
누군가의 얼굴을 알 수 있다 그러나 그들의 마음은 그렇지 않습니다.
You've only known me for a few days,
당신은 나를 안 지 며칠밖에 안 됐어요,
so how much can you possibly know about me?
그럼 당신은 얼마나 할 수 있나요? 나에 대해 알아?
Don't trust others so easily.
남을 너무 쉽게 믿지 마세요.
The human heart is treacherous—
인간의 마음은 믿을 수 없습니다—
far more complex and unpredictable
훨씬 더 복잡하고 예측 불가능
than the matters of cultivation.
재배의 문제보다
It's always better
항상 더 좋아
to be cautious.
조심해야 합니다.
It's getting late.
점점 늦어지고 있어요.
You should go now.
지금 가세요.
[Xin Xie Manor]
[신시에 저택]
[Sheng, Xin Xie Manor]
[Sheng, Xin Xie Manor]
I still have some matters
아직 문제가 좀 있어
to take care of here,
여기서 처리해야 할 일이 있어
so it'll be a while before I can return.
그러니까 내가 돌아올 수 있기까지는 시간이 좀 걸릴 거야.
Also,
또한,
Sheng is very obedient and well-behaved.
Sheng은 매우 순종적이고 잘 행동합니다.
If you don't provoke her,
그녀를 자극하지 않는다면,
she won't give you any trouble.
그녀는 당신에게 어떤 문제도 일으키지 않을 것입니다.
You two get along well at home
두 분은 집에서 잘 지내세요
and wait for me to come back.
그리고 내가 돌아올 때까지 기다리세요.
I still have some matters
아직 문제가 좀 있어
to take care of here,
여기서 처리해야 할 일이 있어
so it'll be a while before I can return.
그러니까 내가 돌아올 수 있기까지는 시간이 좀 걸릴 거야.
Also,
또한,
Sheng is very obedient and well-behaved.
Sheng은 매우 순종적이고 잘 행동합니다.
If you don't provoke her,
그녀를 자극하지 않는다면,
she won't give you any trouble.
그녀는 당신에게 어떤 문제도 일으키지 않을 것입니다.
♪ The moon rises, bright and fair ♪
♪ 달이 떴다, 밝고 공정하게 ♪
♪ A graceful beauty, soft and rare ♪
♪ 우아한 아름다움, 부드럽고 희귀한 ♪
♪ She soothes my troubled, restless heart ♪
♪ 그녀는 내 고민을 달래주고, 불안한 마음 ♪
♪ So elegant and radiant ♪
♪ 정말 우아하고 빛나네요 ♪
[Madam Flower]
[플라워 부인]
♪ Soft and swaying ♪
♪ 부드럽고 흔들리는 ♪
The Chongling Valley Pill-Tasting Competition
충링 계곡 약 맛보기 대회
is still some time away.
아직 시간이 좀 남았습니다.
So be it.
그렇게 하세요.
I'll take shelter from the rain at the inn tonight.
비를 피할게요 오늘 밤 여관에서.
Wake up.
깨우다.
Wake up now.
지금 일어나세요.
Excuse me...
죄송합니다...
[An]
[안]
Leave.
떠나다.
Hurry up and leave.
서둘러 떠나세요.
It's about to rain outside.
밖에 비가 내리려고 합니다.
Where are you going, Miss?
어디 가세요, 아가씨?
Could it be my humble inn is too shabby
내 초라한 여관이 너무 초라한 건 아닐까
to meet your standards, Miss?
당신의 기준에 맞추려고요, 아가씨?
I forgot to feed my horse.
나는 말에게 먹이를 주는 것을 잊었다.
I can send someone to do it.
그 일을 하도록 사람을 보낼 수 있어요.
How could I trouble you to do it yourself?
당신이 직접 하도록 내가 어떻게 귀찮게 할 수 있겠습니까?
An,
안,
go do it.
가서 해봐.
Please, have a seat.
앉으세요.
Your hands are so cold.
손이 너무 차갑네요.
Let me get you some warm wine
따뜻한 와인 좀 가져다 드릴게요
to warm you up.
당신을 따뜻하게하기 위해.
Wine... Wine...
와인... 와인...
Wine!
와인!
Landlady,
집주인,
2 more jars please.
2병 더 주세요.
Great wine.
훌륭한 와인.
It's him.
그 사람이에요.
[Fulai Inn]
[푸라이 인]
Come with me quickly.
빨리 나와 함께 가세요.
Why? Where to?
왜? 어디로?
Stop drinking and come with me.
술 그만 마시고 나랑 같이 가.
I haven't finished my wine yet.
아직 와인을 다 마시지 못했습니다.
Come with me, you.
나와 함께 가세요.
Sorry for the wait, Sir.
기다리게 해서 죄송합니다, 선생님.
Fine wine's coming right up.
좋은 와인이 바로 나오네요.
Please enjoy.
즐겨주세요.
Here comes the wine.
여기 와인이 왔어요.
Thank you for your kindness, Landlady,
친절하게 대해주셔서 감사합니다, 집주인님,
but I don't drink.
하지만 나는 술을 마시지 않습니다.
This wine only warms the body.
이 와인은 몸만 따뜻하게 해줍니다.
It won't make you drunk.
그것은 당신을 취하게 만들지 않을 것입니다.
This wine doesn't make you drunk.
이 와인은 당신을 취하게 만들지 않습니다.
That's how you know it's good wine.
그래야 좋은 와인이라는 걸 알 수 있죠.
Listen to him. Just take a sip.
그의 말을 들어보세요. 그냥 한 모금 마셔보세요.
I think I'll still pass.
아직은 합격할 것 같아요.
Come on.
어서 해봐요.
Who dares disturb my sleep?
누가 감히 내 잠을 방해하겠는가?
[Lord of Rust-Sword, bounty guard of Dongzhou Prefecture]
[러스트 소드의 군주, 현상금 경비원 동주현]
Sir, if you wish to stay,
선생님, 머물고 싶으시면
there are comfortable beds upstairs.
위층에는 편안한 침대가 있습니다.
If you want to continue your journey,
여행을 계속하고 싶다면
we have raincoats and umbrellas to offer.
우리는 비옷과 우산을 제공합니다.
How come you went and slept on my beam
왜 내 침대에 가서 잤어?
without saying a word?
아무 말도 없이?
That's hardly the conduct of a gentleman, is it?
그런 행동은 거의 아니야 신사 맞죠?
I'm an official,
나는 공무원이에요
not a gentleman.
신사는 아닙니다.
I don't like sleeping in beds,
나는 침대에서 자는 걸 좋아하지 않아
nor do I enjoy going out in the rain.
비오는 날 외출하는 것도 좋아하지 않습니다.
I just want a sip of warm wine.
따뜻한 와인 한 모금 마시고 싶을 뿐이에요.
Landlady,
집주인,
why don't you join me for a drink?
나랑 같이 한잔하는 게 어때?
What's wrong?
무슨 일이야?
Won't you give me this courtesy?
나한테 이런 예의를 베풀지 않을래?
I have no intention of being your enemy.
나는 당신의 적이 될 생각이 없습니다.
Unfortunately,
불행하게도
someone has reported you to the Dongzhou Prefecture,
누군가가 당신을 신고했습니다 동저우현으로
saying you got hungry at midnight
자정에 배가 고프다고 말했어
and devoured someone's husband.
그리고 남의 남편을 잡아먹었습니다.
I've come to claim the bounty.
현상금을 받으러 왔습니다.
I'm afraid this calamity today
오늘은 이런 재앙이 닥칠까 걱정이네요
is one you cannot escape.
벗어날 수 없는 것입니다.
You have a death wish?
죽고 싶은 소원이 있나요?
You,
당신은
take that drunkard away!
그 술고래를 데려가라!
Wake up!
깨우다!
Come with me!
나와 함께 가자!
Sit down for a bit.
잠시 앉아보세요.
I thought it was a snake or scorpion,
뱀이나 전갈인 줄 알았어요,
but it's just a red-headed centipede.
하지만 그건 그냥 빨간 머리 지네일 뿐이에요.
What are you doing?
뭐하세요?
Celestial stem Ding, earthly branch Si,
천상의 줄기 딩, 땅의 가지 Si,
the five elements rotation requires yin fire.
다섯 가지 요소 회전 음의 불이 필요합니다.
Interesting.
흥미로운.
I didn't expect that you're a cultivator.
나는 당신이 수련인이라는 것을 예상하지 못했다.
It was actually an illusion?
사실 착각이었나?
It's dead?
죽었나요?
Well, I stepped in.
글쎄요, 제가 개입했어요.
Of course I could take down a mere bug.
물론 단순한 버그를 제거할 수도 있습니다.
Since I can't bring back its head,
머리를 되돌릴 수 없기 때문에
a hairpin will do.
머리핀이면 됩니다.
You said you came to claim the bounty,
현상금을 받으러 왔다고 하셨는데요,
and you're in an official uniform.
그리고 당신은 공식 유니폼을 입고 있습니다.
Are you a government official?
당신은 정부 공무원입니까?
I stand by my name and reputation.
나는 내 이름과 명성을 옹호합니다.
I'm a bounty guard from Dongzhou Prefecture,
나는 현상금 경비원이야 둥저우현,
known as Lord of Rust-Sword.
Rust-Sword의 군주로 알려져 있습니다.
I'm Xin Mei from Xin Xie Manor.
저는 Xin Xie Manor의 Xin Mei입니다.
You're a mediocre cultivator with average talent
당신은 평범한 수련자입니다 평균적인 재능을 갖고
and ordinary martial skills,
그리고 일반적인 무술 기술,
yet you've got quite some nerve,
그래도 넌 꽤 용기가 있어,
daring to enter a shabby little inn like this
과감히 입장하다 이런 허름한 작은 여관
in the middle of nowhere.
아무데도 없는 곳에.
I just came in to take shelter from the rain.
방금 들어왔어 비를 피하려고.
I didn't think much about it.
나는 그것에 대해 많이 생각하지 않았습니다.
So it was not bravery,
그러니 그것은 용기가 아니었습니다.
but rather foolishness.
오히려 어리석다.
You...
당신은...
Anyway, thank you for your help, Warrior.
어쨌든, 도와줘서 고마워요, 전사님.
If you really want to thank me,
정말로 나에게 감사를 표하고 싶다면
give me some money.
나에게 돈을 좀 줘.
I've been chasing this centipede demon
난 이 지네 악마를 쫓아왔어
for over 300 li,
300리 이상,
and my boots are worn out.
그리고 내 부츠는 낡았어.
You don't have money?
돈이 없나요?
My master did give me some when I left the mountain,
주인님이 나한테 좀 주셨어 내가 산을 떠났을 때,
but now
하지만 지금은
I've spent almost all of it.
거의 다 썼어요.
Landlady, I've fed the horse and...
여주인님, 제가 말에게 먹이를 줬는데...
Now we know what to have for dinner.
이제 우리는 저녁으로 무엇을 먹어야 할지 알았습니다.
Go get some firewood to start a fire.
가서 불을 피우려면 장작을 좀 가져와라.
This room is cold and damp.
이 방은 춥고 습해요.
I'm freezing.
나는 얼어붙고 있다.
This little rabbit demon hasn't harmed anyone.
이 작은 토끼 악마 누구에게도 해를 끼치 지 않았습니다.
How do you know?
어떻게 알 수 있나요?
It's been trembling with fear.
두려움에 떨고 있었습니다.
Go on.
계속하세요.
Why did you let it go?
왜 놔두셨나요?
Whether human or demon,
인간이든 악마이든
there's always good and evil, right and wrong.
항상 선과 악이 있고, 옳고 그름.
This little rabbit hasn't done anything wrong,
이 작은 토끼 아무 잘못도 하지 않았어
so you shouldn't hurt it.
그러니까 상처주지 말아야지.
Fine.
괜찮은.
All that effort for nothing.
그 모든 노력은 헛되지 않았습니다.
Miss cultivator,
미스 재배자,
can you mend boots?
부츠를 고칠 수 있나요?
No.
아니요.
You have no skills whatsoever,
넌 기술이 전혀 없어,
yet you dare travel alone?
그런데 감히 혼자 여행을 갈 수 있겠어?
Are you a cultivator too?
당신도 수련하는 사람입니까?
You've never heard of my name?
내 이름을 들어본 적 없나요?
I'm ranked second on the List of Top Martial Artists,
난 2순위야 최고의 무술가 목록에
known as "Lord of Rust-Sword."
"러스트 소드의 제왕"으로 알려져 있습니다.
I'm a human,
나는 인간이에요
not a cultivator.
재배자가 아닙니다.
That's impressive,
정말 인상적이네요
being able to fight evil spirits
악령과 싸울 수 있어
as a mere mortal.
단순한 필사자로서.
Of course.
물론.
I aim to achieve sainthood through martial arts.
나는 성인이 되는 것을 목표로 삼는다 무술을 통해.
Once my divine sword is unsheathed,
내 신검이 뽑히면,
no demons or monsters,
악마나 괴물은 없어
not even immortal sect cultivators,
심지어 불멸의 종파 경작자,
will be a match for me.
나에게 맞는 경기가 될 것입니다.
You're awake.
당신은 깨어있습니다.
Have some water.
물 좀 드세요.
Thank you, Miss.
고마워요, 선생님
I was drunk earlier.
나는 일찍 취했다.
I drank myself into a stupor,
나는 술에 취해서 혼수 상태에 빠졌어,
and now my stomach feels bloated.
이제 배가 더부룩해지는 것 같아요.
It feels really bad.
정말 기분이 안 좋아요.
Mr. scholar.
학자님.
Do you have any money?
돈이 있나요?
Money?
돈?
Yes, I do.
네, 그렇습니다.
I'm heading to the capital for the imperial exam,
수도로 가는데 임페리얼 시험을 위해
and I brought some travel funds.
그리고 여행 자금도 좀 가져왔어요.
Look,
보세요,
the road to the capital is dangerous.
수도로 가는 길은 위험하다.
You should get yourself a guard
경비원을 구해야 해
to escort you to the capital.
당신을 수도까지 호위하기 위해.
That won't be necessary.
그럴 필요는 없습니다.
The money I brought
내가 가져온 돈
is only enough for myself.
나 자신에게는 충분합니다.
I'm going to sleep.
나는 자러 갈거야.
Do as you please.
원하는 대로 하세요.
Thank you for the water, Miss.
물 고마워요, 선생님
You're welcome, Sir.
천만에요, 선생님.
Actually,
실제로
this isn't the first time we've met.
우리가 만난 것은 이번이 처음이 아닙니다.
That day at Heyan Restaurant,
그날 Heyan 레스토랑에서
we had a brief encounter.
우리는 짧은 만남을 가졌습니다.
What a coincidence.
정말 우연이군요.
To be honest with you, Sir,
솔직하게 말씀드리자면, 선생님,
I have something to ask.
물어볼 게 있어요.
That day I heard
그날 난 들었어
from what you said
네가 말한 것 중
that it seems there's more
더 많은 것 같은데
to Lord Lu's case.
루 경의 경우.
Is that true?
그게 사실인가요?
You know Lord Lu, Miss?
루 경을 아시나요, 아가씨?
Are you from Wei County?
웨이현 출신이신가요?
Yes,
네,
but I haven't been home for a long time.
하지만 나는 오랫동안 집에 없었어요.
I just returned recently.
최근에 돌아왔습니다.
Then what do you think
그러면 어떻게 생각하세요
has changed in Wei County?
웨이현이 바뀌었나요?
I think
내 생각엔
there aren't many significant changes.
중요한 변화는 많지 않습니다.
That's odd.
이상하네요.
The great flood six months ago,
6개월 전 대홍수,
with 2 months of non-stop rain,
2개월 동안 계속 비가 내렸어요
affected all 9 counties of Yong region.
용 지역 9개 군 전체에 영향을 미쳤다.
Walls collapsed,
벽이 무너졌다
families wept, and countless people died.
가족들은 울었고 수많은 사람들이 죽었습니다.
In Caomen County,
차오먼 현에서는
Jiangping County
장핑현
and Lishan County,
및 리산 현,
flat lands became rivers,
평지가 강이 되었고,
low areas flooded over 10 feet deep,
낮은 지역이 10피트 깊이로 침수되었습니다.
and countless homes of officials and commoners collapsed.
그리고 수많은 관료들의 집 평민들은 무너졌습니다.
Even today,
오늘도
there are still few signs of life,
아직 생명체의 흔적이 거의 없어요
just yellow sand and withered grass,
그냥 노란 모래와 시든 풀뿐이야,
a vast wasteland.
광대한 황무지.
How could Wei County remain so prosperous?
웨이 현은 어떻게 그렇게 번영을 유지할 수 있었습니까?
Perhaps
아마도
the flooding in Wei County
웨이현 홍수
wasn't as severe as in other counties?
다른 카운티만큼 심하지 않았나요?
Wei County is located in a low-lying area
웨이 현은 저지대에 위치하고 있습니다
and borders the Cao River.
카오 강(Cao River)과 접해 있습니다.
Its position is even worse
그 위치는 훨씬 더 나쁩니다
than the other counties.
다른 카운티보다.
So why did it remain unharmed?
그렇다면 왜 무사히 남아 있었습니까?
Why?
왜?
It was because of Lord Lu.
루 경 때문이었습니다.
Since Lord Lu took office,
루 경이 집권한 이후
he's always focused on repairing the dikes
그는 항상 제방을 수리하는 데 집중하고 있어요
and reinforcing the levees.
그리고 제방을 강화합니다.
When the flood arrived,
홍수가 났을 때,
he even led the able-bodied personally,
그는 심지어 건강한 신체를 가진 사람들을 개인적으로 이끌었습니다.
working day and night, and it was only through this effort
밤낮으로 일하고, 그리고 그것은 오직 이러한 노력을 통해서만 가능했습니다
that Wei County's livelihood was preserved.
그 웨이 카운티의 생계 보존되었습니다.
Then does that mean
그렇다면 그 말은
his defiance of the imperial edict—
그의 제국 칙령에 대한 반항—
his refusal to control grain prices—
그의 곡물 가격 통제 거부—
was all just an act?
다 그냥 행위였나요?
That part was true.
그 부분은 사실이었습니다.
Initially, the 9 counties jointly ordered
처음에는 9개 카운티 공동 주문
that merchants be forbidden from inflating grain prices.
상인들이 금지되어 있는 것 곡물 가격을 부풀린다.
Any grain priced above 100 wen per dou
1두당 100원 이상의 곡물
could not be traded.
거래할 수 없었습니다.
But Lord Lu
하지만 루 경
did the exact opposite.
정반대로 행동했습니다.
He raised the price of grain
그는 곡물 가격을 올렸다
to 180 wen per dou.
1개당 180원까지.
The people couldn't afford to eat,
사람들은 먹을 여유가 없었어요
so naturally they resented him.
그러니 당연히 그들은 그를 원망했다.
So why did he do that?
그렇다면 그는 왜 그랬을까요?
Is it true as people say
사람들이 말하는 게 사실인가요
that he took...
그가 가져간 것...
That he took bribes from grain merchants?
곡물 상인에게서 뇌물을 받았다고?
At first, that's what I thought too.
처음에는 나도 그렇게 생각했다.
But take a look at the other 8 counties
하지만 좀 보세요 나머지 8개 카운티
that restricted grain prices.
곡물 가격을 제한한 것입니다.
Merchants couldn't sell at high prices,
상인들은 높은 가격에 팔 수 없었어요
so they simply hoarded their grain
그래서 그들은 단순히 곡물을 비축해 두었어요
and refused to sell any,
판매를 거부했고
let alone transport it to Yong region.
용 지역으로 운송하는 것은 물론입니다.
The people could only starve to death at home.
사람들은 단지 집에서 굶어죽어요.
Among the 9 counties,
9개 현 중
only Wei County allowed high-priced grain sales.
웨이현만 허용됨 고가곡물판매.
As a result,
그 결과,
grain merchants flocked to Wei County.
곡물 상인들이 웨이현으로 모여들었다.
Scarcity increases value.
희소성은 가치를 증가시킵니다.
With more grain available,
더 많은 곡물을 사용할 수 있게 되면
the price actually came down.
실제로 가격이 내려갔습니다.
Only those who took the trouble
문제를 겪은 사람들만
to investigate closely would notice
자세히 조사해 보면 알 수 있을 것 같아
that Wei County's high-priced grain
그 웨이 현의 고가 곡물
was only sold for less than 2 months.
2개월도 채 지나지 않아 판매되었습니다.
So you're saying
그럼 당신은
he actually did a good thing?
그 사람이 정말 좋은 일을 했다고?
It was a good thing indeed.
참으로 좋은 일이었습니다.
But people only remember
하지만 사람들은 기억만 해요
that he drove up grain prices at first,
그가 처음에 곡물 가격을 올렸다고
causing them to starve,
굶어죽게 만들어
without understanding the bigger picture.
더 큰 그림을 이해하지 못한 채.
As for the imperial court,
황실에 관해서는
with so many people starving to death in this disaster,
정말 많은 사람들과 이 재난으로 인해 굶어 죽었어요
they needed someone to blame.
그들은 비난할 누군가가 필요했습니다.
But...
하지만...
I still feel that Lord Lu's punishment
나는 아직도 루 경의 형벌을 느낀다
was determined too hastily.
너무 성급하게 결정했다.
In the past, the Court of Judicial Review
과거에는 사법심사법원
had sentenced officials to death by 1,000 cuts before,
관리들에게 형을 선고했다 1,000컷 전에 사망,
but such an inhumane and cruel punishment
하지만 이렇게 비인간적이고 잔인한 처벌은
normally had to be reported step by step—
일반적으로 단계별로 보고해야 했습니다.
from the prefecture and county up to the capital,
현과 군에서 수도까지,
until the Emperor approved it.
황제가 승인할 때까지.
Yet...
아직...
Yet Lord Lu's crime was determined
하지만 루 경의 범죄는 결정되었습니다
in less than half a month.
한달 반도 안되어.
That really was too fast.
정말 너무 빨랐어요.
If everything you said is true,
당신이 말한 모든 것이 사실이라면,
then why didn't Lord Lu
그럼 왜 루 경은
appeal or proclaim his innocence?
그의 결백을 호소하거나 선언합니까?
The 9 counties are in collusion,
9개 카운티가 공모하고 있습니다
all speaking and acting from the same playbook.
말하고 행동하는 모든 것 같은 플레이북에서.
No flaws can be found.
결함을 찾을 수 없습니다.
At a time like this,
이런 때에는
anyone who acts differently
다르게 행동하는 사람
becomes the one that sticks out—
튀어나온 것이 됩니다—
the scapegoat.
희생양.
Who could he turn to
그는 누구에게 의지할 수 있었나요
for justice?
정의를 위해?
If that's really the case,
정말 그렇다면
how much injustice
얼마나 불의한 일인가
must Lord Lu have suffered?
루 님께서 고통을 받으셨을까요?
Lord Lu,
루 경,
is there truly no injustice
정말 불의는 없나요
in your case?
당신의 경우에는?
Public opinion has spoken.
여론이 이야기되었습니다.
How could there be any injustice?
어떻게 불의가 있을 수 있겠습니까?
Don't trust others so easily.
남을 너무 쉽게 믿지 마세요.
The human heart is treacherous—
인간의 마음은 믿을 수 없습니다—
far more complex and unpredictable
훨씬 더 복잡하고 예측 불가능
than the matters of cultivation.
재배의 문제보다
It's always better
항상 더 좋아
to be cautious.
조심해야 합니다.
Lu Huai,
루 화이,
it's time to go.
이제 갈 시간이다.
♪ Caught in fate's design, I search my soul ♪
♪ 운명의 설계에 사로잡혀, 나는 내 영혼을 탐색한다 ♪
♪ What should I do to avoid living my life in vain? ♪
♪ 피하려면 어떻게 해야 하나요? 내 인생을 헛되이 살고 있습니까? ♪
♪ My blade stays clean, untouched by dust ♪
♪ 내 칼날은 깨끗하게 유지됩니다. 먼지가 닿지 않은 상태 ♪
♪ Yet it's sparked thousands of wars ♪
♪ 그러나 그것은 수천 번의 전쟁을 촉발시켰습니다 ♪
♪ Soul consumed, bones remade— I accept it all ♪
♪ 영혼은 소모되고 뼈는 다시 만들어지는데 다 받아들인다 ♪
♪ Embracing pain as home, reborn like a phoenix ♪
♪ 고통을 집처럼 받아들이고, 불사조처럼 다시 태어났어요 ♪
♪ Just to trade the rest of my days for one true life as a human ♪
♪ 그냥 내 남은 시간을 교환하려고요 인간으로서의 진정한 삶을 위해 ♪
It's truly satisfying to see justice served!
정말 만족스럽습니다 정의가 실현되는 것을 보기 위해!
♪ Let strong wine carry me into drunken nights till midnight ♪
♪ 강한 와인이 나를 데려가도록 해주세요 밤새 술에 취해 자정까지 ♪
♪ Let my soul blaze in brilliant colors ♪
♪ 내 영혼이 찬란한 색깔로 불타오르게 해주세요 ♪
♪ Let the agony of a thousand cuts ♪
♪ 천 컷의 고통을 놔두세요 ♪
♪ Stand as proof that I have lived ♪
♪ 내가 살았다는 증거로 삼아라 ♪
♪ Let me taste a life of flesh and blood in full ♪
♪ 살과 피의 삶을 맛보게 해주세요 전부 ♪
♪ Let me savor the many flavors of the mortal world ♪
♪ 다양한 맛을 맛보게 해주세요 필멸의 세계의 ♪
Execute him! Execute him!
그를 처형하라! 그를 처형하라!
♪ Let me face the world's warmth and cold alike ♪
♪ 세상과 마주하게 해주세요 따뜻함과 차가움 모두 ♪
♪ To live and perish with it, daring to go mad, daring to dream ♪
♪ 그것과 함께 살고 멸망하는 것, 대담하게 미쳐가고, 과감하게 꿈을 꾸세요 ♪
Hurry up and execute him!
서둘러서 그를 처형하세요!
It's the 3rd quarter of noon!
3분기 정오입니다!
♪ Don't live in vain ♪
♪ 헛되이 살지 마세요 ♪
Execute!
실행하다!
♪ Let strong wine carry me into drunken nights till midnight ♪
♪ 강한 와인이 나를 데려가도록 해주세요 밤새 술에 취해 자정까지 ♪
♪ Let my soul blaze in brilliant colors ♪
♪ 내 영혼이 찬란한 색깔로 불타오르게 해주세요 ♪
What's wrong with this girl?
이 소녀에게 무슨 문제가 있는 걸까요?
♪ Let the agony of a thousand cuts ♪
♪ 천 컷의 고통을 놔두세요 ♪
Are you okay?
괜찮으세요?
♪ Stand as proof that I have lived ♪
♪ 내가 살았다는 증거로 삼아라 ♪
♪ Let me taste a life of flesh and blood in full ♪
♪ 살과 피의 삶을 맛보게 해주세요 전부 ♪
♪ Let me savor the many flavors of the mortal world ♪
♪ 다양한 맛을 맛보게 해주세요 필멸의 세계의 ♪
♪ Let me face the world's warmth and cold alike ♪
♪ 세상과 마주하게 해주세요 따뜻함과 차가움 모두 ♪
♪ To live and perish with it, daring to go mad, daring to dream ♪
♪ 그것과 함께 살고 멸망하는 것, 대담하게 미쳐가고, 과감하게 꿈을 꾸세요 ♪
♪ Let strong wine carry me into drunken nights till midnight ♪
♪ 강한 와인이 나를 데려가도록 해주세요 밤새 술에 취해 자정까지 ♪
Make way!
길을 비켜라!
♪ Let my soul blaze in brilliant colors ♪
♪ 내 영혼이 찬란한 색깔로 불타오르게 해주세요 ♪
Let me through!
통과시켜주세요!
♪ Let the agony of a thousand cuts ♪
♪ 천 컷의 고통을 놔두세요 ♪
♪ Stand as proof that I have lived ♪
♪ 내가 살았다는 증거로 삼아라 ♪
♪ Let me taste a life of flesh and blood in full ♪
♪ 살과 피의 삶을 맛보게 해주세요 전부 ♪
♪ Let me savor the many flavors of the mortal world ♪
♪ 다양한 맛을 맛보게 해주세요 필멸의 세계의 ♪
♪ Let me face the world's warmth and cold alike ♪
♪ 세상과 마주하게 해주세요 따뜻함과 차가움 모두 ♪
♪ To live and perish with it, daring to go mad, daring to dream ♪
♪ 그것과 함께 살고 멸망하는 것, 대담하게 미쳐가고, 과감하게 꿈을 꾸세요 ♪
♪ Don't live in vain, have a pleasant journey of life ♪
♪ 헛되이 살지 마세요. 즐거운 인생 여행 되세요 ♪
He was truly a man of steel.
그는 그야말로 강철의 사나이였습니다.
He endured the execution for so long
그는 너무 오랫동안 처형을 견뎌냈습니다
without uttering a single word.
한마디도 하지 않고.
How many cuts did he take?
그는 몇 컷을 찍었나요?
Did you count?
세어봤어?
Don't you know about
Don't you know about
Executioner Wang's skills?
에 대해 모르시나요? 왕집행관의 실력?
No one could have a good end under his blade.
누구도 좋은 결말을 가질 수는 없어 그의 칼날 아래서.
There must have been
있었음에 틀림없어
at least 1,000 cuts.
최소 1,000컷.
1,000 cuts?
1000컷?
Could someone so strong-willed
누군가 그렇게 의지가 강한 사람이 있을까
really be a corrupt official?
정말 부패한 공무원인가요?
Who can say that for sure?
누가 확실히 말할 수 있습니까?
But the high grain prices were real,
하지만 높은 곡물 가격은 진짜였습니다.
and the fact that people starved to death was also real.
그리고 사람들이 굶어죽었다는 사실도 역시 진짜였어.
Stop looking. Let's go.
그만 찾아보세요. 갑시다.
[Wei County]
[웨이 현]
This...
이것은...
Snowing at this time of year?
이맘때쯤 눈이 오나요?
When snow falls at such a time,
이럴 때 눈이 내리면
it means there's been a grave injustice.
그것은 심각한 불의가 있었다는 것을 의미합니다.
It shouldn't be snowing at this time of year.
눈이 오면 안 돼 이맘때쯤.
What's going on?
무슨 일이야?
Indeed.
물론.
Snowing at this time of year must mean a great injustice has occurred.
이맘때에 눈이 내리는 것은 다음을 의미합니다. 큰 불의가 일어났습니다.
That's right.
좋아요.
So heavy.
너무 무거워요.
Look how heavy the snow is.
눈이 얼마나 무거운지 보세요.
He must have been wronged.
그는 틀림없이 부당한 대우를 받았을 것입니다.
Even heaven can't bear to watch.
천국도 지켜볼 수 없습니다.
It's snowing.
눈이 온다.
Have something to eat.
먹을 것을 가져라.
The authorities ordered his body to be exposed for 3 months
당국은 그의 시신을 명령했다 3개월 동안 노출될 예정
to appease public anger.
대중의 분노를 진정시키기 위해.
This night
오늘 밤
is going to be long.
길어질 것입니다.
Do you think
네 생각엔
Lord Lu was wrongfully executed?
루 경이 부당하게 처형당했다고요?
His confessions are all signed and sealed,
그의 고백은 모두 서명되고 봉인되었습니다.
written in black and white.
흑백으로 작성되었습니다.
There can't be any injustice.
불의가 있을 수는 없습니다.
But it's snowing at this time of year.
그런데 이맘때쯤에는 눈이 내립니다.
Even heaven is protesting his innocence.
하늘조차 그의 결백을 항의하고 있다.
Do you think Lord Lu
루 경
was truly wronged?
정말 잘못한 거야?
Watch your words.
당신의 말을 조심하십시오.
This case was personally investigated
이 사건은 개인적으로 조사된 사건입니다
by Lord Song,
송경 님,
and the punishment was set by the Court of Judicial Review.
그리고 처벌은 정해졌다 사법 검토 법원에 의해.
Whether it's right or wrong,
맞든 틀리든
the higher-ups will decide.
윗사람이 결정할 것이다.
We just need to follow orders without question.
우리는 명령을 따르기만 하면 된다 의심의 여지없이.
Who's there?
거기 누구 있어요?
Where's the body?
시체는 어디에 있나요?
[Tomb of Lu Huai]
[루화이 묘]
Master said
스승님이 말씀하셨어
that as someone from the immortal sect,
불멸의 종파에 속한 사람으로서
to achieve the great path,
큰 길을 이루려면
I must remain steadfast,
나는 굳건함을 유지해야 해,
untainted by the mortal world,
필멸의 세계에 오염되지 않은
and free from karmic entanglements.
카르마의 얽매임에서 벗어나요.
But this time when I came down the mountain,
하지만 이번에는 내가 산을 내려왔을 때,
I broke my vows
서약을 어겼어
and forcibly tied a marriage bond with you.
그리고 강제로 묶인다 당신과의 결혼 유대.
I regret it in my heart,
마음 속으로 후회해요
but the consequences are already set
하지만 결과는 이미 정해져 있어
and cannot be undone.
취소할 수 없습니다.
All I can do now is stride forward.
지금 내가 할 수 있는 일은 앞으로 나아가는 것뿐이다.
Lord Lu.
루님.
I really must leave now.
이제 정말 떠나야 해요.
I need to get medicine for my master.
주인님께 약을 구해야 해요.
But don't worry,
하지만 걱정하지 마세요.
I'll burn plenty of paper offerings for you
종이 공양을 잔뜩 태울게요 당신을 위해
so you can live
네가 살 수 있게
comfortably and peacefully in the underworld.
편안하고 평화롭게 지하세계에서.
Also,
또한,
those buried around here
이 근처에 묻혀 있는 것들
are all my relatives.
모두 내 친척이에요.
They're all kind and gentle,
다들 친절하고 온화해요
and I believe they'll
난 그들이 그럴 거라고 믿어
treat you well
잘 대해줘
and get along with you.
그리고 당신과 함께 지내십시오.
[Wei County Government]
[웨이 현 정부]
Take care.
잘 지내세요.
Chu.
추.
You were doing so well here.
여기서 정말 잘 지내셨어요.
Why are you quitting?
왜 그만두나요?
Indeed.
물론.
People out there
밖에 있는 사람들
are all competing to get in
모두 들어가기 위해 경쟁하고 있어
and become a bailiff.
그리고 집행관이 되세요.
It's a secure job, you know—
그건 안전한 직업이잖아요, 아시다시피—
steady for life.
평생 꾸준한.
How...
어떻게...
How can you just
어떻게 그냥
decide to quit like that?
그렇게 그만두기로 했어?
Life
인생
has different paths for everyone.
사람마다 다른 길을 가지고 있습니다.
I'm too restless.
나는 너무 불안하다.
I'm not cut out for this job.
나는 이 일에 적합하지 않습니다.
Then what job are you cut out for?
그럼 당신은 무슨 직업 때문에 잘렸나요?
Can't you tell?
당신은 말할 수 없습니까?
With this face,
이 얼굴로는
I should be living off women.
나는 여자를 먹고 살아야한다.
Alright then.
그럼요.
I'm leaving.
나는 떠난다.
Alright.
괜찮은.
Take care.
잘 지내세요.
Chu! Chu!
츄! 츄!
Chu!
츄!
Don't go, Chu! Don't go!
가지 마, 츄! 가지 마세요!
Chu, don't go!
츄, 가지 마!
Don't go!
가지 마세요!
[Tomb of Lu Huai]
[루화이 묘]
How long have you been awake?
얼마나 오랫동안 깨어 있었나요?
About 3 days.
약 3일.
Since I was quitting the job,
직장을 그만둔 이후로
there has been one drinking party after another.
있었다 연달아 술자리.
What can I say? I'm just popular.
내가 무엇을 말할 수 있습니까? 나는 단지 인기가 있다.
For a demon,
악마의 경우
you're really committed to acting human, aren't you?
당신은 정말 인간적으로 행동하는 데 전념하고 있어요. 그렇지 않나요?
Of course.
물론.
What are you waiting for? Let's keep going.
당신은 무엇을 기다리고 있습니까? 계속 해보자.
Do you think the Wang family of Jinqiu
Jinqiu의 Wang 가족이
is truly a family of cultivators?
정말 수련하는 가족인가?
Is the young master of the Wang family
왕 가문의 젊은 주인인가
really a cultivator?
정말 재배자인가?
Of course it's true.
물론 사실이에요.
I've heard their ancestors
그들의 조상에 대해 들어본 적이 있어요
included a Nascent Soul cultivator.
Nascent Soul 경운기가 포함되어 있습니다.
That's incredibly impressive.
정말 인상적이네요.
A Nascent Soul cultivator?
초기 영혼 경작자?
Isn't that close to ascending to godhood?
가깝지 않은가 신의 자리에 오를까?
You clearly don't understand.
당신은 분명히 이해하지 못합니다.
Cultivators in the immortal sect
불멸의 종파의 수련자들
are divided into 10 realms:
10개의 영역으로 나누어져 있습니다:
Qi Cultivation, Foundation Building,
기 재배, 기초 건물,
Golden Core, Nascent Soul, Cave Void,
황금 코어, 초기 영혼, 동굴 공허,
Soul Projection, Integration,
영혼 투영, 통합,
Great Completion, Tribulation Crossing,
위대한 완성, 환란의 교차점,
and Deity Transformation.
그리고 신의 변신.
But since the God-Demon War,
하지만 신-마 전쟁 이후,
the heavenly ladder collapsed,
하늘의 사다리가 무너졌어,
and spiritual energy in the world has become increasingly scarce,
세상의 영적인 에너지와 점점 부족해졌어요
making cultivation more difficult than ever.
재배를 하다 그 어느 때보다 어렵습니다.
Not to mention Tribulation Crossing or Deity Transformation,
트리뷸레이션 크로싱은 말할 것도 없고 또는 신의 변신,
even Cave Void and Soul Projection cultivators
심지어 동굴 공허 및 소울 프로젝션 재배자
are hard to find.
찾기가 어렵습니다.
These days, if there's
요즘에는
a Nascent Soul cultivator in a sect,
종파의 초기 영혼 경작자,
they can dominate an entire region.
그들은 전체 지역을 지배할 수 있습니다.
The Wang family of Jinqiu used to be so prestigious
진추왕씨(晉丘王氏) 예전에는 정말 유명했었지
that they wouldn't even bother with people like us.
그 사람들은 신경도 쓰지 않을 거라고 우리 같은 사람들.
It was only after
It was only after
their Nascent Soul ancestor
이후였죠 Nascent Soul의 조상
passed away
세상을 떠났다
that their family declined like this.
가족들이 이렇게 거절했다고요.
I've also heard that
나도 그런 말을 들었어
this generation of the Wang family
이 세대의 Wang 가족
has no descendants with immortal perception.
후손이 없다 불멸의 인식으로.
Even the young master of the Wang family
심지어 왕가의 젊은 주인
is also just an ordinary person.
그도 그냥 평범한 사람이다.
That I don't know.
나는 모른다.
Anyway, all the War Demons are dead,
어쨌든, 전쟁 악마는 모두 죽었어,
and the Youhu Clan won't descend from the mountains.
그리고 Youhu 일족은 강림하지 않을 것입니다 산에서.
The Twelve Immortal Sects have all the power now.
12개의 불멸의 종파 이제 모든 힘을 가지세요.
Even the Emperor himself
심지어 황제 자신도
has to show them respect.
그들에게 존경심을 보여야 합니다.
Gentlemen,
여러분,
here's your wine.
여기 당신의 와인이 있습니다.
Please enjoy.
즐겨주세요.
Want one?
하나 원하시나요?
Nah.
아니.
Just drinking, no food?
술만 마시고, 음식은 없나요?
Yep,
응,
just drinking, no food.
술만 마시고, 음식은 없어요.
You know me.
당신은 나를 알고 있습니다.
So you still don't feel like eating.
그래서 아직도 먹고 싶지 않은 것 같아요.
Hu.
후.
Take a break.
휴식을 취하세요.
Come and have some water.
와서 물 좀 드세요.
Okay.
좋아요.
The road is rough. Be careful.
길은 험난하다. 조심하세요.
This uneven road needs to be leveled.
이 울퉁불퉁한 길은 수평을 맞춰야 합니다.
Otherwise, someone might fall and break their teeth,
그렇지 않으면 누군가 넘어질 수도 있어요 그리고 이빨을 부러뜨려
and no one's going to take care of them.
그리고 아무도 그들을 돌보지 않을 것입니다.
I have my wife to take care of me.
나는 나를 돌봐줄 아내가 있다.
Xin Mei.
신 메이.
Thank you
감사합니다
for agreeing to marry me.
나와 결혼하기로 동의했기 때문입니다.
Lord Lu.
루님.
Do you have any other wishes?
다른 소원이 있나요?
As your wife,
당신의 아내로서,
is there anything I can do for you?
내가 당신을 위해 할 수 있는 일이 있나요?
I still feel that
아직도 그런 느낌이 들어
Lord Lu's punishment
루 경의 처벌
was determined too hastily.
너무 성급하게 결정했다.
In the past, the Court of Judicial Review
과거에는 사법심사법원
had sentenced officials to death by 1,000 cuts before,
관리들에게 형을 선고했다 1,000컷 전에 사망,
but such an inhumane and cruel punishment
하지만 이렇게 비인간적이고 잔인한 처벌은
normally had to be reported step by step—
일반적으로 단계별로 보고해야 했습니다.
from the prefecture and county up to the capital,
현과 군에서 수도까지,
until the Emperor approved it.
황제가 승인할 때까지.
Yet...
아직...
Yet Lord Lu's crime
하지만 루 경의 범죄
was decided in less than half a month.
보름도 채 안되어 결정됐다.
No.
아니요.
This matter cannot end like this.
이 문제는 이대로 끝날 수 없습니다.
Miss.
미스
This road is difficult,
이 길은 험난해
and there are landslides.
그리고 산사태도 있어요.
This road is full of potholes.
이 길은 움푹 들어간 곳으로 가득 차 있습니다.
You're all alone.
당신은 혼자입니다.
If you fall, there won't be anyone to help you up.
넘어지면, 당신을 도와줄 사람은 아무도 없을 거예요.
You should find an easier path.
더 쉬운 길을 찾아야 합니다.
Come on, let's get back to work.
자, 다시 일하러 갑시다.
Excuse me, gentlemen.
실례합니다, 여러분.
Could you please tell me
나에게 말해주실 수 있나요
how to get to the capital?
수도에 어떻게 가나요?